A Guide to the Department of Conservation and Development, Division of History, Records, 1927-1950
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Records, 1927-1950
Library of Virginia
24806a-c, 25913 and 41571
49.52 cubic feet
Department of Conservation and Development, Division of History
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Accessions 24806a-c transferred from History Division, Virginia State Library on 30 June 1958; Accession 25913 transferred from Historic Publications Division, Virginia State Library on 21 November 1963; Accession 41571 transferred to Archives on 29 November 2004.
Historical Information
The Virginia State Commission of Conservation and Development was created in 1926 to consolidate and coordinate a number of conservation agencies including the Water Power and Development Commission, the State Geological Commission, the State Geological Survey, Office of the State Geologist, Office of the State Forester, and the Division of Parks. Governor Harry F. Byrd appointed his campaign manager William E. Carson (1870-1942) as the Commission's first chairman. Between 1926 and 1950 the Commission changed names several times: Virginia State Commission of Conservation and Development (1926-1938), Virginia Conservation Commission (1938-1948) and Department of Conservation and Development (1948-1985). Chairman of the Commission included: William E. Carson (1926-1935), Wilbur C. Hall (1935-1939), N. Clarence Smith (1939-1942), and William A. Wright (1942-1948). In 1948, the General Assembly, as part of a reorganization of state government abolished the Virginia Conservation Commission and created the Department of Conservation and Development. The new agency took over the function of the Conservation Commission, State Port Authority and the State Planning Board. Governor William Tuck named Wright as director of the new Department of Conservation and Development.
In 1927, Carson created the Division of History and Archaeology within the Commission to preserve and develop the historical resources of the state. The new Division was lead by Dr. H.J. Eckenrode, Director; Colonel Bryan Conrad, Assistant Director; and M.F. Pleasants, Field Assistant. Carson believed that Virginia needed to publicize Virginia's wealth of history and tradition especially to out-of-state travelers. He decided to have markers placed on the states' highways to provide information of historical events that had happened in their vicinity. By the beginning of World War II, the Commission had erected more than 1400 historical markers across Virginia.
In addition to the historical marker program, the Division of History assisted in the development of Virginia history in many other ways. It cooperated with the federal government in studying the battlefield of Yorktown and in the development of the Richmond Battlefield Park. The Division photographed thousands of colonial era houses and other significant structures. The Division sponsored the Federal Writers' Project for Virginia and conducted the WPA's Virginia Historical Inventory.
The Commission suspended the historical marker program during World War II because of rationing of metals. In its place, the Commission inaugurated a War records program including a newspaper reference file and a correspondence program in which a non-salaried correspondent from each locality sent reports about local war time activities and local war activities and reaction to the war. In addition, the Division began a program to locate and mark the graves of distinguished Virginians. Finally in 1949, the Division published The Hornbook of Virginia History that included a brief history of Virginia and other historical information.
Scope and Content
The Department of Conservation and Development, Division of History, Records are housed in 108 boxes, 3 oversize boxes, and 1 oversize map case drawer. The collection is arranged into five (5) series. Series have been designated for: I. Correspondence; II. Virginia War History Project; III. Graves of Distinguished Virginians Project; IV. Records; and V. Historical Material. These records include addresses articles, correspondence, maps, magazines, minutes, newspapers, newspaper clippings, pamphlets, photographs, postcards, programs, radio addresses, reports scrapbooks and telegrams. These records document Virginia state government's development and promotion of the Commonwealth's history and historical resources.
The creation and administration of Virginia's Historical Marker program is well documented in the records (Series I). This series provides a wealth of information on the Division's approach to markers, their construction, inscription, installation and maintenance. Of note to the Civil War Historian, this series also contains records on the creation of the Richmond Battlefield Park. Included are correspondence, maps, pamphlets and aerial photographs taken of the battlefield in the 1930s.
For researchers interested in the life on the home front during World War II, there are some records of note. The Division of History collected reports on home front conditions. Topics include local opinion and reaction to war events and news, rosters of local service men and women, activities of local organizations, economic conditions and religious conditions (Series II).
The Division of History and Archaeology also attempted to locate graves of distinguished Virginians (Series III) and created a reference file on Virginia History and eventually published The Hornbook of Virginia History (Series IV). The Historical Material files is essentially a ready reference collection containing newspaper clippings and historical sketches on historic sites and events. (Series V).
Oversize items are filed in 3 boxes and 2 map case drawers. The oversize records consist primarily of maps and newspapers. Oversize items, which were part of the regular sized filing unit, were removed from their perspective folders. A separation notice listing the item(s) separated and their new location was put in its place. For location and content list of oversize folders, see the listing at the end of the container list.
It is recommended that the researcher read the series level scope and content notes thoroughly before accessing the collection.
Arrangement
Organized into the following series:
I. Correspondence, 1927-1950 (Accession 24806a)
II. Virginia War History Project, 1942-1946 (Accession 24806b)
III. Graves of Distinguished Virginians Project, 1944-1950 (Accession 24806c)
IV. Records, 1929-1950 (Accession 25913)
V. Historical Material, 1927-1950 (Accession 41571)
Contents List
- Series I. Correspondence, 1927-1950 (Accession 24806a)
  The Correspondence series is housed in 70 boxes with oversized material separated and is arranged into two subseries. Subseries have been designated for Correspondence and Correspondence, Dead File. It is unknown why some correspondence were separated from the general correspondence (Subseries A) and grouped with the correspondence, dead file (Subseries B), because there is some overlap between the subseries. The series consists primarily of incoming and outgoing correspondence from Division of History staff members including: Dr. Hamilton J. Eckenrode, Director (1927-1949), J.R.V. Daniel, Director (1949-1950), Bryan Conrad, Assistant Director and M.F. Pleasants, Field Assistant. This series comprises a large and important section of the Division of History records. In this series, researchers have a complete view, from 1927- 1950, of most of the correspondence sent and received by the Division of History. These correspondence provide insight into the workings of the historical marker program including inscriptions, locations, and manufacturing, instillation and maintenance of markers, and the Division's promotion of history and other activities.
  - Subseries A: Correspondence, 1927-1950
    This subseries is housed in 55 boxes, one oversize box and two oversize map folders and is arranged alphabetically with subdivisions for general correspondence, additional correspondence and topics. This is the larger of the two subseries and contains a variety of letters from individuals across the county interested in Virginia history and the historical marker program. Topics include historical inquiries, historical marker inscriptions, investigation of the historical marker program by other states, and the Richmond Battlefield Park. Other topics include work of the Division during World War II, Shenandoah National Park, birthplace of the Wright Brothers mother, and biographical information on Dr. Hamilton J. Eckenrode and Bryan Conrad.
    The History Division responded to general historical questions concerning Virginia history from historians, history buffs and students from every part of the country. Virginia's historical marker program was a model for other states and there are inquiries about the program from individuals from Alabama, Florida, Georgia, Illinois, Massachusetts, Michigan, New Jersey, New York, North Carolina, Ohio, Oklahoma, and West Virginia. Many of these letters provide detailed information about the marker system (Eckenrode to Douglas Arant, 31 August 1938) and a summary of how to install markers (Pleasants to Arthur Adams, 24 April 1931).
    This subseries is a great source of information on the creation of the Richmond Battlefield Park. Included is a booklet by Eckenrode titled "History of the Richmond Battlefield Parks" dated 23 February 1932, aerial photographs of the park taken in the early 1930s by the United States Army Air Corps as well as correspondence, memorandums and reports on the creation of the park. Several maps of the battlefield from the early 1930s are filed under oversized. Additional information on the Richmond Battlefield Park is located with the correspondence of William E. Carson, Douglas Southall Freeman and Branch Spalding (Subseries B, Correspondence, Dead File).
    Correspondence with William A. Wright, chairman of the Virginia Conservation Commission (1942-1948) include a report on the work of the History Division during World War II (5 August 1947) and two memorandums from Eckenrode describing the Division's plans and work during the war (12 August 1944 and March 1946). Information on the Shenandoah National Park includes newspaper clippings, the dedication program of the park (3 July 1936), and three pamphlets: "Shenandoah National Park Project" (n.d.), "A Brief History of the Beginning of the Movement for a National Park in Northern Virginia - Now Known as the Shenandoah National Park" (ca. 1934), and "The Shenandoah National Park Travelogue" (1937). Correspondence between Orville Wright and Wilbur Hall (1932-1933 filed under Wright Brothers ) concern the birthplace of Wright's mother in Virginia. Biographical information on Eckenrode ( Rowland Egger ) and Conrad ( P. Tulane Atkinson, 14 July1945) is also included. Other notable topics include the Bell Tower ( John Garland Pollard, 26 February 1931, 11 October 1932), the State Seal (Pollard, 25 August 1931) and the Growth of the Conservation and Development Commission (Box 13, Folder 9) that includes a brief history and newspaper clippings.
    Correspondents include William Sumner Appleton, John Stewart Bryan, Harry F. Byrd, Arthur Kyle Davis, Sr., E. Griffith Dodson, Dr. J.D. Eggleston, E.O. Flippen, Douglas Southall Freeman, Richard A. Gilliam, Wilmer L. Hall, Douglas McArthur, John Garland Pollard, Branch Spalding, and William A. Wright.
    - General Correspondence
      - AAA-Adams (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Adamson-Allen (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Allison-Amos (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Ancarrow-Anderton (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Andrews-Archer (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Architectural Book Publishing Company - Associated Transport Inc. (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Atkins-Ayres (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Additional Correspondence and Topics
      - A.C.L. Railroad (Historic Places on Line) (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - Act for Establishing Ports and Towns (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - Acts of General Assembly (See General Assembly file)
      - Adams, Dr. Arthur, Edgewater Park, NJ (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - Adjutant General, Washington, DC (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - Agriculture and Immigration of Virginia, Department of (publications) (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - Albright, Horace M. (Colonial National Monument, etc.) (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - Alsberg, Henry G., Director, WPA Writers Guide Project, Washington, DC (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - American Association for State and Local History (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - American Historical Association (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - Andrews, Dr. Matthew Page, Baltimore, MD (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Ashbury, Dr. Samuel E. (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - Association for the Preservation of Virginia Antiquities (APVA) (Box 2, Folder 13)
      - Automobile Accident Insurance (Lumbermens Mutual Casualty Company) (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - Automobile - Forms and Receipts (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - General Correspondence
      - Bachelder, W.K. - Baker, H.P. (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - Baker, Henry E. - Ballagh, James Curtis (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - [Wm] Balantyne & Sons - Barnett, S.P. (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - Barney, Alice P. - Batchelor, Ellen M. (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - Bates, W.B. - Beale, Robert C. (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - Bealle, Morris A. - The Bedford Democrat (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - Bedsaul, F. Clyde, Mrs. - Bennett, J. Gordon (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Bentley, E.B., Mrs. - Beverley, William (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - Bickel, Karl A. - Blair, Ruth (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - Blake, George McD. - Blyth, James (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - Board, L.I., Mrs. - Booker, George E., III (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - Booker, Marshall B. - Bowcock, Mildred E. (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - Bowen, E.W. - Bozarth, Lester E. (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - Bradbury, Eugene - Brewer, Jr., R.L. (Box 5, Folder 2)
      - Brewick, G. Millard - Brookfield, John, Mrs. (Box 5, Folder 3)
      - Brooks, Evelyn V. - Bruce, Fannie Maupin (Box 5, Folder 4)
      - Bruce, Fisher, Mrs. - Buck, Walter H. (Box 5, Folder 5)
      - Buckey, M.C. - Burkholder, C.S., Mrs. (Box 5, Folder 6)
      - Burnley, W. Sam - Bywaters, H.F. (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Additional Correspondence
      - Baird, Alvin V., Delaplane, VA (Box 6, Folder 2)
      - Batchelder, F.R. (Massachusetts Tercentennial & Marker Program) (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - Bevan, Dr. Arthur, Charlottesville, VA (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - Bigger, Mrs. T.H. (Box 6, Folder 5)
      - Blanchard, Mrs. F.T., Bristol, TN (Box 6, Folder 6)
      - Bland, S. Otis (Box 6, Folder 7)
      - Booker, Marshall D., Halifax, VA (Commissioner) (Box 6, Folder 8)
      - Bowen, Homer K., Executive Secretary, Southwest Virginia, Inc., Wytheville, VA (Box 6, Folder 9)
      - Bradford, J.H. (Director of Budget Division) (Box 6, Folder 10)
      - Bridges, Major-General Charles H., War Department, Washington, DC (Box 6, Folder 11)
      - Bridges, J. Malcolm (Editor, Richmond Magazine) (Box 6, Folder 12)
      - Brooks, J. Callan (Box 6, Folder 13)
      - Browning, J.W., Clerk, Orange County Circuit Court (Box 7, Folder 1)
      - Bruce, Dr. P.A., University of Virginia (Box 7, Folder 2)
      - Brush, Edward H., Paeonian Springs, VA (Box 7, Folder 3)
      - Brydon, Dr. G. MacLaren, Richmond, VA (Box 7, Folder 4)
      - Budget Recommendations, 1929-1930, 1936-1950 (Box 7, Folder 5)
      - Buford, R.P. (Box 7, Folder 6)
      - Bulkley, Mrs. Caroline Kemper (Box 7, Folder 7)
      - Bushnell, David I., Jr. (Box 7, Folder 8)
      - Byrd, Harry F. (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Topics
      - Birds in Virginia (Box 7, Folder 10)
      - Book Reviews (by Hamilton J. Eckenrode) (Box 7, Folder 11)
      - Books (Secondhand) (Box 7, Folder 12)
      - Books (Reference) in State Library (County and City) (Box 7, Folder 13)
      - Bulletin (Weekly Activities of Commission on Conservation and Development) - See News Letter (Box 7, Folder 14)
      - Burial Places of Famous Virginians (Box 7, Folder 15)
      - Byrd's "VA-NC" Line (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - General Correspondence
      - Cabaniss, Robert - Campbell, William S. (Box 8, Folder 1)
      - Canada, W.H., Mrs. - Carrington, T.C. (Box 8, Folder 2)
      - Carroll, E.M. - Cary, V. Ferguson, Mrs. (Box 8, Folder 3)
      - Casey, A.M. - Cawood, Myrta Ethel (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - Chaffee, C.B., Mrs. - Cheatwood, Joyce (Box 8, Folder 5)
      - Cheek, H.R. - Choate, McLin S., Mrs. (Box 8, Folder 6)
      - Chrisman, Thomas L. - Clark, Thomas W. (Box 9, Folder 1)
      - Clarke, E.C. - Clore, R.W., Mrs. (Box 9, Folder 2)
      - Closson, W.P. - Coghill, Elizabeth A. (Box 9, Folder 3)
      - Cohen, John S. - Colonna, W.B. (Box 9, Folder 4)
      - Colton, Dan B. - Conway, Ray (Box 9, Folder 5)
      - Cooch, Edward W. - Copps, Michael, Mrs. (Box 9, Folder 6)
      - Corbell, John D. - Coverston, P.A. (Box 10, Folder 1)
      - Covington, H.H., Mrs. - Craighill, G. Peyton (Box 10, Folder 2)
      - Cramer, J.L. - Crow, C.L. (Box 10, Folder 3)
      - Crowder, Charles W. - Cuthriell, Harry (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Additional Correspondence
      - Calrow, Major Charles J., Consultant-Director, State Planning Board (Box 10, Folder 5)
      - Cammerer, Arno B., Director, National Park Service, Washington, DC (Box 10, Folder 6)
      - Campbell, T. Beverly, Richmond, VA (Box 10, Folder 7)
      - Carrington, T.M., Richmond, VA (Box 10, Folder 8)
      - Carson, Mrs. William E. (Carson Papers of Conservation Commission) (Box 10, Folder 9)
      - Chatelain, Verne E., National Park Service, Washington, DC (Box 11, Folder 1)
      - Chorley, Kenneth (Box 11, Folder 2)
      - Chowning, C.C. (Box 11, Folder 3)
      - Coleman, L.V., Washington, DC (American Association of Museums) (Box 11, Folder 4)
      - Coleman, R.V. (Editor, Dictionary of American History) (Box 11, Folder 5)
      - Conrad, Bryan (Box 11, Folder 6)
      - Cook, Roy Bird (Box 11, Folder 7)
      - Cragon, Gladys W. (Huguenot Society) (Box 11, Folder 8)
      - Cramton, Louis C. (Colonial National Monument) (Box 11, Folder 9)
      - Crittenden, Dr. C.C. (North Carolina Historical Commission) (Box 11, Folder 10)
      - Cronyn, George W., Assistant Director, WPA Writers Guide Project (Box 11, Folder 11)
      - Crouch, Kenneth E. (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Topics
      - Campaign of 1781 (LaFayette-Cornwallis-Phillips-Arnold-Wayne) (Box 11, Folder 13)
      - Campaign of 1781 (Von Steuben) (Box 11, Folder 14)
      - Campaigns of 1st and 2nd Manassas (Suggested Inscriptions) (Box 11, Folder 15)
      - Campaign of 1862 (Seven Days Battle) (Box 12, Folder 1)
      - Campaign of 1862, Diary of (Movements of Jackson's Army) (Box 12, Folder 2)
      - Campaign of 1862 and 1864 (Seven Days Battles), Suggested Inscriptions (Box 12, Folder 3)
      - Campaign of 1864 (Cold Harbor) (Box 12, Folder 4)
      - Chambers of Commerce, List of (Box 12, Folder 5)
      - China's Children Fund, Inc. (Box 12, Folder 6)
      - Commonwealth of Virginia - See Nickname of Virginia
      - Confederate Ordnance (Box 12, Folder 7)
      - Congress (Newspaper article) (Box 12, Folder 8)
      - Conservation and Development Commission, Growth of (Box 12, Folder 9)
      - [Virginia] Conservation Commission (Laws of Virginia) (Box 12, Folder 10)
      - Constitution of the United States and Tree Planting Instructions (Box 12, Folder 11)
      - Counties, List and Organization (Box 12, Folder 12)
      - Court House Markers (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - General Correspondence
      - Dabney, Charles William - Davenport, P.J. (Box 12, Folder 14)
      - Davidson, H.L. - Davis, John W. (Box 12, Folder 15)
      - Davis, Levin Nook - DeLancy, J. Lawrence (Box 13, Folder 1)
      - Delaney, T.C., Mrs. - Dickinson, Sally B. (Box 13, Folder 2)
      - Dickson, C.G. - Dodds Granite Company (Box 13, Folder 3)
      - Dodge, Harrison H. - Duermyer, Louis (Box 13, Folder 4)
      - Duffy, Elizabeth F. - Dyer, J.P. (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Additional Correspondence
      - Darden, Colgate W., Governor of Virginia (Box 13, Folder 6)
      - Daughters of the American Revolution (D.A.R.) (Box 13, Folder 7)
      - Davidson, D.N., Orange, VA (Box 14, Folder 1)
      - Davis, Private Creed T. (Diary from 4 May 1861 to 20 February 1865) [typed transcript - original at the Virginia Historical Society] (Box 14, Folder 2)
      - Demaray, A.E. (Colonial National Monument, etc.) (Box 14, Folder 3)
      - Denny, Bishop Collins (Box 14, Folder 4)
      - Dillon, Jesse W. (State Treasurer, 1948) (Box 14, Folder 5)
      - Dodson, E. Griffith (Box 14, Folder 6)
      - Dyson, Mrs. Mabel L. (Natural Wonders Questionnaires) (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - General Correspondence
      - Eakins, Mrs. Mary - Edwards, R.A. (Box 14, Folder 8)
      - Edwards, Mrs. R.B. - Ellis, Wade H. (Box 14, Folder 9)
      - Ellison, Charles J. - Essig, Lester C. (Box 14, Folder 10)
      - Etheridge, R. Bruce - Eyler, Helen L. (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Additional Correspondence
      - Early, Jr., N.B. (Box 15, Folder 2)
      - Eckenrode, Hamilton J. (Box 15, Folder 3)
      - Eggleston, Dr. J.D. (Box 15, Folder 4)
      - Ellison, R.P. (Executive Secretary, Dept. of Highways) (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Topics
      - Education in the South: A Documentary History of (Box 15, Folder 6)
      - Employees Merit Rating (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - General Correspondence
      - Faber, Forris E. - Fellers, P.A. (Box 15, Folder 8)
      - Felt, George G. - Finney, Mrs. Ruth B. (Box 16, Folder 1)
      - Fippin, Betty C. - Fitzhugh, William Bullitt (Box 16, Folder 2)
      - Fitzpatrick, F.B. - Fletcher, William Meade (Box 16, Folder 3)
      - Flippin, Mrs. O.G. - Foshee, R.H. (Box 16, Folder 4)
      - Foss, Carl A. - Francis, Mrs. Paul Hart (Box 16, Folder 5)
      - Frank, Thomas E. - Freeman, Margaret (Box 16, Folder 6)
      - French, H.S.W. - Furnell, W.W. (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Additional Correspondence
      - Farrar, Thomas L., Charlottesville, VA (Box 17, Folder 2)
      - Fippen, E.O. (Box 17, Folder 3)
      - Fishburn, Junius P., Roanoke, VA (Box 17, Folder 4)
      - Flickinger, B. Floyd (Superintendent Colonial National Monument) (Box 17, Folder 5)
      - Fothergill, Mrs. A.B. (Box 17, Folder 6)
      - Freeman, Douglas Southall (part one) (Box 17, Folder 7)
      - Freeman, Douglas Southall (part two) (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - Topics
      - Flags of the Confederacy and the United States (Box 17, Folder 9)
      - Folklore and Folksongs (Box 17, Folder 10)
      - Fredericksburg Battlefield Park Association (Box 17, Folder 11)
    - General Correspondence
      - Gahn, Bessie Wilmarth - Gardner, William R. (Box 17, Folder 12)
      - Garges, Samuel - Gee, Virginia (Box 18, Folder 1)
      - Geiger, Frances H. - Gillespie, W.G. (Box 18, Folder 2)
      - Gillett, Charles A. - Goode, Virgie C. (Box 18, Folder 3)
      - Goodhart, Henrietta McCormick - Goyne, William J. (Box 18, Folder 4)
      - Grabeel, Charles E. - Green, E.L. (Box 18, Folder 5)
      - Green, Floyd F. - Griffin, Mrs. R.L. (Box 18, Folder 6)
      - Griffith, Albert H. - Gulick, J.S. (Box 19, Folder 1)
      - Gurney, Hubert A. - Gwyn, Mrs. T. Lenoir (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - Additional Correspondence
      - Gaines, Francis P. (Box 19, Folder 3)
      - Garrett and Massie, Inc. (Mark A. Rollins) (Box 19, Folder 4)
      - Gathright, A.B. (Director of Purchasing Division) (Box 19, Folder 5)
      - Gilliam, Charles Edgar (Box 19, Folder 6)
      - Gilliam, Richard A. (Box 19, Folder 7)
      - Glass, Senator Carter (Box 19, Folder 8)
      - Glass, Jr., Carter (Box 19, Folder 9)
      - Gooch, Winslow L. (Box 19, Folder 10)
      - Goolrick, John T. (Box 19, Folder 11)
      - Gordon, Armistead C. (Box 19, Folder 12)
      - Grayson, Mrs. J. Cooke (Box 19, Folder 13)
      - Groome, H.C., Warrenton, VA (Box 19, Folder 14)
    - Topics